We will get started.
Well, temporarily leaving the land of systems
to talk about more deep learning stuff, which we're
going to have two lectures on scaling law and scaling
law adjacent phenomena.
So today is going to be the basics.
We're just going to talk about pretty basic scaling law stuff.
Some of the classic works.
How does the basic idea of scaling laws
connect to maybe things you know about from machine learning 101.
And then in two lectures, we're going
to do the more advanced version of the scaling laws
lecture, where we're going to basically go
into a bunch of modern, open model tech reports, things
like mu P and other parameter initializations,
and this year I'm going to throw in some more
stuff for optimizers.
So there will be an advanced version
of this that will try to really get to the cutting edge.
Today, we're going to start with all the really basic stuff.
And due to some scheduling constraints,
next lecture will be inference, so you're
going to go back and forth.
You're going to do scaling laws and inference and then scaling
laws again.
So scaling laws is really the following scenario in some ways,
or you run into it very quickly once you run into this scenario.
So you have your very wealthy friend,
who has given you 10,000 B200s for a month,
and he or she has asked you to build a very good open source
language model.
They would like to get something out of those B200s.
And so you've already put together your infra team.
That's your assignment to buddies.
And you have, let's say a good pre-training data set.
That's going to be the assignment after this,
but let's say you already have that.
And then you're going to go and train a big model,
but there's lots of choices in training a big model— all
the assignments, the earlier lecture two stuff that we had
earlier, where you have questions like what architecture
should I use?
What should my hyperparameters be?
And it's very scary to run these things
on a run that is basically, potentially
millions of dollars in cost, so how
do you really take this idea of scaling up very seriously?
How do you make sure that your big run is actually successful?
So of these many choices, some of which
you're going to just copy out of the literature.
The stuff that I talked about earlier in the architecture
lecture is really about well-adopted best practices,
and you will probably just pick some of these out of a hat.
That's fine, but really, let's say you're at the frontier.
You would like to build something
that's actually better than the best available models today.
You have to start really optimizing these.
You can't just copy the choices of others
and get something that's better than the state of the art.
So how do we do that?
Well, that's going to require us to really engage
with this idea of scaling.
So scaling laws have been one very powerful tool.
You might also call it a paradigm.
Scaling laws, if you talk to some people who are really
in these big labs doing scaling work,
it's almost kind of a way of life.
They're like, we really believe in the scaling laws.
It's almost a belief, and you'll see
why scaling laws can sometimes be quite tricky objects.
But really, scaling laws are these simple, predictive rules
of how to go from small scale model performance and behavior,
and to try to extrapolate them up to large scale behavior.
And so the basic naive way to approach model training
might be to say, I have a big budget,
I'm going to do multiple training runs on these very
big runs, and I'm going to tune hyperparameters
on those big runs, but that's very wasteful.
So instead, what I would like to do
is I would like to do all of my optimization at the small scale
and have some simple rule that allows
me to extrapolate small scale behaviors to large scale
behaviors.
And if the small scale and large scale
are connected by some very simple, robust connections
like regularities of some kind, then you
would have confidence in this kind of new scaling approach
to optimizing your system.
And that's really what today is all
going to be about-- this engineering view of a scaling law.
And to start with, I'm going to talk a little bit
about background, because scaling laws are very
interesting in that not only are they the newest paradigm, that's
how a lot of these models are designed and thought,
but also they connect very closely to very classical ideas.
So if you're a person that's a machine learning theorist,
actually, there are some things that you will really
feel at home with in some ways, so they're like empirical sample
complexities.
And then I'll talk through the history of scaling laws of one
kind and show you that this is not something that's really new.
It's something with actually quite a bit of history
and research done to it.
So I really, really had to put some math into my slides.
I really feel the need to do so, but one
of the things that is very interesting
is that for the longest time, machine learning
has thought about this question of how will my model perform,
especially from a theory perspective?
I have this model class, how good is my model going to be?
And generalization bound is the theorists answer
to this question, so you have your error,
over some finite hypothesis class,
and you say, oh, my error is going
to be at most this much worse than the model's
performance on my training set.
This is classic generalization bounds.
You can write this down for more complex classes
like smooth densities or whatever,
but importantly, not only does this
tell you some of performance, notice
that these bounds are often dependent on the sample size.
And so this is telling you, well, this a theoretical upper bound on my loss values
as a function of how my training set grows.
And in some ways, that's very closely related to this idea
of what happens as I scale up the amount of data that I have?
Those are closely related questions,
where you might believe me that that's true.
And if you try to figure out what is the very first scaling
law paper that exists?
It turns out you can go back quite far.
You can go back to Bell Labs and Corinna Cortes and Vladimir
Vapnik and these folks that were doing very serious theory
work on machine learning, ask this question, well,
training classifiers on a really large data set
is often very expensive.
We would like to avoid doing that,
and to do so maybe we can just fit classifiers on a smaller
sample, fit a curve to how their error rates decay,
and use that as a way to estimate their performance.
That's almost literally a data scaling law back in 1993.
So this idea, at the very least, thinking
about how your model's performance
changes as a function of data set size is just a very
classical one, and there's a lot of work that
supports this kind of idea.
I just want to connect this to some of these older ideas
so you don't really think of scaling laws as this very
new, purely neural thing.
It's an idea that has a lot of roots in empirical machine
learning, and also connections to theoretical machine learning.
And if you start to look at the history of this,
there's a lot of people that have said, isn't it the case
that maybe instead of spending money on algorithm development,
maybe we should just go collect more data,
because if we plot how the performance of our systems
behave as a function of the amount of data that we have,
it turns out that they are all increasing or improving
in predictable ways?
Banko and Brill, is one of the canonical NLP references in how
the amount of data and thinking about scaling
is a really valid way of improving system performance,
so there's lots of ways of thinking about this.
And there's also work by other NLP folks
like Kolachina et al. in 2012.
This is one of the earlier works on different kinds
of functional forms for scaling laws, where once again, they're
increasing the amount of data that they're using to train.
In this case, machine translation systems or BLEU scores.
And they're asking like, what is the right functional form
for how a model's performance behaves
as a function of increased data amount?
And they maybe surprisingly or not surprisingly,
end up with the same power laws, which is pow 3 and 4 as really
we do today.
For the rest of the lecture, you're
going to keep seeing essentially these polynomial functions, pow
3 and pow 4 as I talk about scaling laws.
And we knew about a lot of this back in the 2010s
that these kinds of functional forms
were very predictive of model behavior as we scaled them up.
And then finally, I really like mentioning this paper because
for whatever reason, they don't get,
or Hestness et al. don't get cited
quite as much as they should.
The origins of neural scaling, I would point back
to Hestness in 2017.
Really a very forward looking work
in many ways that built these scaling
laws as a function of data set size
for a wide variety of systems, different kinds of speech
recognition systems, machine translation systems, language
models, and they showed that these things follow
these nice polynomial trends across a really large number
of domains.
And it was really ahead of its time,
because 2017 was long before some of the earlier OpenAI
scaling laws and so on in the 2020s.
And they talked about stuff that we talk about today,
like emergence, where suddenly models
可能会展现出某些类型的能力
因为准确率是一个更加不连续的度量
而不是损失。
而实际上，按计算量进行缩放，如果我们有系统
能够可预测地扩展到大规模训练数据，那么
计算量确实会变得非常重要。
最后，既然我们按计算量进行缩放，那么
速度和系统优化将会转化为准确率。
所以在某些方面，我们今天看到的很多事情，
比如系统缩放的现象等等，
我们本可以知道，或者我在2017年本可以知道，
如果我当时阅读并思考了这些缩放定律论文
并更认真地思考它们。
所以在我讲的每一场缩放定律
讲座中都要提到那篇论文，只是为了说明，很多这些现象
在现代时代之前就早已为人所知，
或者说在现代语言模型时代之前，因为
我们有可能在见到这些大型语言模型之前
就已经知道我们所处的状态。
知道这一点非常酷。
关于这段半历史性的部分有什么问题吗？
是的。
[听不清]，我想知道那些只是纯粹经验上的，还是有什么方法
可以证明这一切的合理性？
你问的是这些缩放定律，
它们从何而来？
这些是纯粹的曲线拟合练习。
我会稍微谈一下缩放定律可能从何而来，
以及为什么多项式可以说是非常自然的一类缩放
定律，但并没有金科玉律说它们只能是这些。
不过我会说，在某些方面，
理论提供了一个非常丰富的地方，缩放定律的
函数形式可以从中而来，因为理论
经常在思考误差率如何衰减
作为各种对象的函数？
它们会给你各种类型的
候选函数形式。
物理学家也非常擅长这个
因为他们思考极限，
比如极限如何表现？
And that gives you different scaling law functional forms.
Cool.
All right, any other questions?
Good.
So now I'm going to start talking about more modern neural
language model scaling, and I'm going
to start with data scaling laws because to me, they're the most
simple and natural objects.
Talking about data scaling laws also
allows me to walk you through very step-by-step on how
we might guess what the functional form of a scaling law
might be and why the polynomial form is a natural one.
And then I'm going to start talking about hyperparameters
and architectures and all sorts of other more exotic objects
that are going to be harder to justify from intuition,
but still turn out to have very nice scaling law behaviors.
One of the things that's remarkable about this scaling
law style analysis has been that these power law relationships
seem to hold for a huge variety of different factors.
So the basic ones that we see in pre-training,
and those are going to be the ones that I'm
going to talk about today.
The usual ones that you see are compute on the x-axis.
This is log compute.
Sorry, on the x-axis, log of test loss on the y-axis,
or log of the data set on x-axis,
log of loss on the y-axis, log of parameters
on x-axis, log of loss, once again, on the y-axis.
So we can get a variety of different x-axes
that you might think of as resources in the log axis.
All of them linearize log test loss here.
You can see also much more exotic scaling laws.
You can see scaling laws that are basically
the equivalent to these in downstream benchmarks.
In those cases, you expect to see a sigmoid functional form
as a function of compute or compute-like quantities.
There's even been many works recently, more
on the forecasting side, where people are doing things
like putting dates as the x-axis.
And strangely enough, at least for these
plots—like the upper envelope of these curves
are often linear in various forms of capabilities.
There's no reason that on this bottom side,
the more exotic scaling laws need to be true.
But it turns out to be the case that, I guess, language model
performance is often much more regular as a function of scale
and resources than it initially might appear.
So to begin with, I'm going to start with data scaling laws.
And data scaling laws are a very simple kind
of univariate relationship that we're going to think about.
So in this world, we're going to fix our model training
procedure.
And in general, unless I say otherwise,
the models are going to generally be
bigger than the data set size.
And I'm going to increase my data set size in a regular way,
and I'm going to see how the error reduces.
And what do we expect out of this relationship?
In general, it's going to be monotone-ish
if we tune our hyperparameters well.
Because we have more data, more data
should help us do better at our task.
The error should decrease.
And if you're doing something like classification, or even
for next token prediction, you should really
go from random guessing to some entropy-like object
where you can't do any better than the irreducible error
of your task.
That's the noise floor.
So we're going to have some sigmoidal-like object over here.
So this is generally what we expect out of our system.
So we're going to start with an empirical observation,
and should make this on your own.
You'll make something that looks roughly
like this in parts of assignment 3,
which is if we just have a very big model,
much bigger than our data set, and we
increase the data set size, and we put that on the log axis,
and on the y-axis, we have log test loss.
Once again, you will find that the two points that you plot
会形成一条非常清晰的线性趋势。
我从 Kaplan 2020 年的论文中取了这个。
我会反复引用这篇论文。
这是 OpenAI 的《神经缩放定律》论文。
他们做了很多漂亮的消融实验和大量漂亮的数据。
现在，这个关系，我
在对数-对数图上画了一条线，
这是一个无尺度或幂律关系。
那这意味着什么？
如果我在对数-对数图上有一条线？
对很多人来说，这可能是显而易见的。
但为了真正强调这一点，
如果某个东西在对数-对数图上是线性的，那
意味着什么？
这意味着我有的误差
是多项式衰减的。
而且，这通常意味着我离
我的渐近线还很远。
因为一旦我接近我的渐近线，
我会逐渐变缓，而不是保持一条直线。
所以让我们看一个例子，只是为了向你展示
缩放定律如何非常自然地出现在一个非常
简单的估计问题上。
所以暂时忘掉语言模型。
这是一门语言模型课，
但现在它是统计课，接下来的一
张幻灯片，或者实际上是两张幻灯片。
不，也许是三张幻灯片。
所以在这种情况下，我想做的是
我想从一堆数据中估计均值。
所以我有一个输入，它是从高斯分布中抽取的。
我要估计这个对象的均值。
我就写下经验均值。
然后，你可以写下误差是多少。
那么期望误差是多少？
这些每个都是高斯分布，
而且 mu hat 是高斯分布，所以我可以写下误差。
那将是 sigma 平方除以 n。
所以，如果你看这个，这就是一个缩放定律。
我写下了误差，而误差，如果我取对数，
is a function of log n, log n being the log x-axis.
So in general, if you can come up
with anything that is essentially
1 over n to the alpha plus some constant,
when you plot that on a log-log plot,
subtracting out the constant term,
you're going to get a scaling law.
So anything of this form, where you have polynomial decay
and errors, is going to end up giving you a scaling law.
And of course, in parametric estimation like mean estimation
or regression, you of course, expect a polynomial rate.
You don't really expect anything else.
And if you've taken your stats estimation courses,
you know that essentially all the classical
models you are expected to have a 1 over n scaling.
If you fit a regression or so on, you might get D over n
or whatever else.
And so if this is true, and this is the origins of scaling laws,
if we plot our lines, we should expect
to see roughly a slope of minus 1
because that's the exponent on the x.
Y equals minus x plus C.
If we fit our neural scaling laws,
we will find that our exponents are quite different.
These exponents-- I've taken from these two
on the left from Hestenes, I've taken the one on the right
from Kaplan.
They're about -0.1, -0.3, -0.1, roughly speaking.
And so what does that mean?
That means this is much slower than estimating a mean
or estimating a linear regression.
So this is much, much slower convergence rate, still
polynomial, but much slower.
Now this is interesting.
It's saying that we're getting these kind
of nice polynomial rates, but the exponents are not so great.
They're -0.1.
Where might you get an estimation rate like this?
Well, you would get this if your model was more nonparametric.
I promise this will be the last statistics
slide of this lecture.
Let's say that I want to estimate now,
instead of a mean, an arbitrary smooth function.
So one thing I could do is, if I'm doing a regression problem,
I have my inputs, x1 through xn.
Let's say they're in the unit box.
I have a little bit of Gaussian noise,
and I have an unknown function f that I would like to estimate.
A trivial estimator for this is I can take my space,
I can cut it up into little 2D boxes of length n
to the negative 1 to the fourth.
And then what's our estimation error?
I'll have square root n boxes.
Each box is going to get square root n samples.
And the error is going to be roughly 1
over square root of n or something.
And in general, if have a D-dimensional function
I would like to estimate in this very nonparametric, arbitrary
way, my error is going to be roughly equal to n
to the negative 1 over d.
So my scaling is going to be y equals negative 1
over D times x.
And so now these kinds more flexible functions, functions
that are more flexible than the linear class,
now have rates in their scaling laws that are not just 1,
they're 1 over D.
And so one mental model that you could have
is that the neural networks I was showing you in these slides
are behaving kind of non-parametric regressors in 10
dimensions, like a nearest neighbor or other kinds
of estimators in 10 dimensions.
That's roughly the rate at which they learn from data.
That's kind of a cool thing to be
able to know just by looking at some of these scaling laws.
Some people have argued this more strongly.
Bari et al. and some other scaling law theory folks
have argued that the scaling law exponents are actually
literally telling us that the neural network
is behaving like a non-parametric smoother,
and so on and so forth.
It's an interesting set of arguments,
and you can buy that intuition to whatever extent you'd like.
I don't quite know how much I truly, truly buy this argument.
There's some of the evidence that might be a little sketchy.
It relies on estimators of intrinsic dimension,
but it's an interesting thing to think about
that somehow these exponents are telling us
how fast are these neural networks really learning.
OK, so actually, I'll pause for the moment here.
That's really the end of the really basic data scaling
law of one distribution, and you sample from it,
and you learn from it.
Is that all clear, like the examples and so on?
Good.
Oh yes, question.
When you say that the model is always larger
than data set size, do you mean one-to-one number of parameters
to number of tokens [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, that's a good question.
So the question was something like,
What do I mean when I say the model is larger
than the data set size?
What I mean is when the model gets small relative to the data,
like you have way more data than you have model size,
you enter this irreducible error regime.
You basically fitted the data as well
as you can for your model class, and you
can't do any better no matter how much data you add.
So we want to--when we're thinking about scaling laws,
we usually want to think about this power law regime, which
is the simpler case.
Either that or you explicitly fit the asymptote
and then you correct for it.
Those are the two things.
So when I say the model is larger than the data,
it can be basically any amount that is larger than the data,
as long as it's in this power law
regime, usually like 10 times bigger than the data, what
have you.
Cool.
Good.
OK, now we are back to other data scaling laws.
So data scaling laws by themselves
are not quite as useful as you'd like them to be.
They just tell you how fast does my model learn.
And that's kind of useful for forecasting.
It's not useful for very much else.
If you want to do engineering, you
are probably interested in other questions,
like what is my optimal data mixture?
What is the best way for me to pick my training
data for my model?
Very useful engineering question.
Should I repeat my data, or should I
just not repeat my data, save the compute for something else?
Or maybe I should repeat some high-quality stuff
and not repeat the low-quality stuff.
I could do various other things with repetition.
There's a lot of different engineering decisions
I can make with data.
So how can scaling laws help us make some of those decisions?
And I think one of the things that's interesting
is if we think a little bit about how classical
models behave.
Data scaling laws, if we think about their origins
as essentially empirical versions of generalization
bounds, they tell us, well, data set composition for many models
really affect the offset of these scaling laws,
but their slopes are actually determined by the model class.
They're not really determined by the distribution themselves.
So the slopes might remain the same,
and only the intercepts might change.
And the intercept might actually be really interestingly shaped.
So this is a case of a toy model with a linear regression
with two different things you can sample from.
If you get only one kind of data,
the errors are high no matter what.
You actually want a mixture of both, right.
So if you write down how this intercept behaves,
you actually start to get some very interesting insights
about how having more data diversity is very helpful.
But what does this practically mean?
Well, practically speaking, what this means
is you can actually fit data scaling laws on mixtures,
and that can help you do some data--
sorry, pre-training, data optimization.
So what does this mean?
Let's say you have two data sources for simplicity.
You have news, and you have Wikipedia.
And how much news to use and how much Wikipedia to use.
How can you determine that?
Well, you can train really small models
on a really small amount of data.
And then you can basically train or you
can fit a function of how different mixture levels affect
your performance.
You can do this while you scale up your models little by little.
And you can see how the trends change.
And you can try to extrapolate that out the exact same way
as you would extrapolate out a data scaling law.
And then you can ask which one will be optimal
if I keep scaling it out to my full training run.
So this is a very simple idea of essentially fitting
a functional form at a small amount of compute,
finding the minimum, and then scaling that guy out.
So this is a data mixing loss paper.
Unfortunately, I think if you talk
to anyone who's done a lot of these data mixture work,
they will tell you reality is a lot more
noisy than this ideal world would suggest.
And really, what has, as far as I know, happened in many cases
is you end up training a bunch of small models.
You pick the best data mix from the small model,
and you just scale that guy up, no scaling law required.
And data decide if you're interested in this kind of thing
is a nice, large-scale empirical study of these kinds of data
mixture things.
And what they found was actually,
if you don't fit a scaling law, and instead you
just pick the best data mix at the small scale,
that works well.
For what it's worth, that's consistent with the argument
that the intercepts differ, but the slopes don't change.
Because if the slopes don't change,
the best mixture at small scale is also the best mixture
at large scale.
OK, another really interesting set
of questions that I'll also mention in the context of data
is repetition.
I think it's increasingly the case that compute is growing,
the amount of data that we have is not growing.
And so there's a lot of people interested
in questions of what happens when you repeat
data more and more times.
And there was a nice study a few years back called "Scaling Data-
Constrained Language Models," where they roughly show
something like up to four epochs with standard training recipes,
you just don't get hurt at all.
But if you go past that point, then actually
your realized scaling law, this dark curve
is much worse than the projected scaling law
if you had fresh data.
That's the dashed line over here.
And you can also, once again, write down a modified functional
form that's generally predictive of the behavior of this scaling
law under repetition.
And we can take this idea even more to the extreme.
This was kind of recent work with Percy
in one of our co-advise students,
where we were asking, like, OK, what
happens if you take this idea to the extreme
and you just consider infinite amounts of compute?
So you're allowed to epoch as many times as you want,
like an infinite amount of times.
What is the best thing that you can get out of this system?
Well, it turns out you can't just
keep repeating passes over the data.
You can't keep making your models bigger.
Those have diminishing returns.
And so you end up reaching for other things,
like ensembling your models to try to squeeze more and more
out of your data.
But really, I think the one thing that I'll point out
that's really interesting is your standard data
scaling laws here in the red.
It's a very nice, predictable improvement in performance
as you increase the amount of data.
We do all sorts of interventions like regularizing and adding
ensembles.
You get improvements in performance,
but the slopes look actually surprisingly similar.
This is a lesson that you'll learn
once you start fitting your own scaling laws, that very,
very often your slopes don't change.
Often, the interventions that you do just
change the intercept of the scaling laws.
One last thing that I'll mention,
because I like this paper in the context of scaling
laws and scaling in general, is that a lot
of the phenomena we care about in data
is actually very scale-dependent.
And one example of this is data filtering.
So if you or I tomorrow decide to filter some data
for the models we're training, we would probably
filter very aggressively.
We would only keep the highest quality stuff
because both you and I don't have very much compute.
So we can't train on all the internet anyway.
We might as well filter down to the most high-quality stuff.
On the other hand, if you have a lot of compute,
then you want to train on more and more stuff
because you're going to not want to repeat
on this very high-quality data.
So as you get more and more compute,
your filter has become looser and looser,
and potentially you start training on stuff
that's lower and lower quality.
So a lot of the things that we often
think about statically, things like data
filtering or the quality of data,
are actually much more dynamic.
As you increase scale, you have to think about
where am I going to get the rest of the data.
The filters can't stay fixed as a function of the data,
and certainly the optimal filters
turn out to not be fixed as a function of scale.
OK, so that's it for data scaling laws.
This is the part that I think is most straightforward to understand.
Even as a stats/ML-minded person,
this stuff is all very simple and straightforward to me.
You increase data, performance gets better
in a very predictable way.
I think this is uncontroversial.
The fact that it does so polynomially for such
a big model is still cool, but nothing really crazy.
So hopefully this is reasonable to all of you
that there's so much predictability when you
increase the amount of data.
Oh, yes.
So on this slide for the pre-training
under infinite compute, so that graph on the right
is linear in both the loss and data set size,
whereas the previous example I gave was log-log scale.
And I was wondering why it's linear in both.
Yeah, so this is a bad axis.
Herman and I just talked about bad axis like this.
This is actually doubling.
So it looks linear, but it's actually log scale.
[LAUGHS] I fixed it now.
You fixed it now.
And the y-axis here, it doesn't look logged,
but the range of this is so small
that linear logs are basically the same.
If you look at the fitted functional forms here,
these are still polynomials.
So we're fitting the same functional forms,
and those are the ones that are plotted here.
This is another point.
I'll get to it at the end of the lecture.
If you only have a tiny slice of a compute range,
很难非常、非常明确地分辨
某个东西是按多项式缩放的
还是按指数缩放的。
因为泰勒近似确实存在。
只要放大得足够多，一切看起来都是线性的。
所以它究竟是多项式
还是某种其他函数形式，你
总是要稍微小心和保持怀疑。
好。
OK。
好，所以这就是关于数据的缩放定律，
在很多方面都很直接。
现在我想谈谈更奇特的缩放形式
以及各种模型工程的缩放定律。
所以我们现在要做的是，
尝试设计大型语言模型。
也许你是个激进派，相信也许 LSTM
才是未来。
比如，为什么我不能用 LSTM 代替 transformer？
我想把我的 B200 算力花在我的 LSTM 上。
或者也许你是另一种激进派，
想用 SGD 来训练。
比如，为什么我不能用 SGD 训练？
你可能也会想。
如果你的资源有限，
你有不同的方式来分配它。
也许你应该把模型训练更久，
也许你训练更大的模型，也许我
应该去收集更多数据。
总是有各种各样的权衡在起作用，
而缩放定律给了我们定量的方式来做
这些权衡，希望如此。
我要从一些简单的超参数
问题开始，比如我如何选择我的架构
或优化器，这些我在
第二讲中谈过的东西。
在那里我给了你这样的视角：也许
你可以研究别人怎么做。
现在我要试着给你一些第一性原理的答案
来回答那些问题，用稍微不同的视角
of trade-offs.
So you have to believe in scaling laws in this lecture,
but as long as you do, you get to try things on your own
and find out.
OK, the very first question we might start with is to say,
Are transformers really better than LSTMs?
LSTMs.
They can work OK, too.
They will fit distributions.
With the advent of things like Mamba,
we know that SSMs can work.
So are they better?
The brute force way to answer this question
is to train a big LSTM GPT-3 or even bigger class of models.
The scaling law way would be to train a bunch of smaller models
and say, I'm going to train my transformer
across a different variety of compute ranges,
and I'm going to train different LSTMs with different numbers
of layers on, once again, a variety
of different compute ranges.
Now, what does this show?
This shows LSTMs have definitely different intercept, maybe even
different slope than the transformer.
And because of this, probably you don't want to pick LSTM.
This plot would justify scaling up the transformer instead
of the LSTM.
And if you look at a lot of the architecture papers
today, like you go look at the Mamba
paper or the gated delta net papers,
they will always have a plot that
looks like this, where you have vanilla transformer, our really
cool model.
And our really cool models, usually either on top or below,
because that's what would prove that your model is doing better.
And you certainly don't want something where your slopes are
worse because that means as you scale up larger and larger,
your models will eventually do worse.
So this is one way of really reasoning
about architectures without training gigantic models.
There haven't been, I think, quite
as many recent and good architecture scaling law papers.
I think the one that is relatively recent
and that I like quite a lot is by Ek and others at Google,
back when they were publishing this kind of work,
where they did a whole bunch of scaling studies on T5-style
models, where they trained larger and larger variants of T5
models on many different architectures.
And I think one thing that's really cool,
and one of the reasons why I still bring this paper up,
is they capture exactly the architecture
changes that we implement today in our frontier models.
So things like performer, which is an efficient attention, that
doesn't scale very well.
We do not implement those.
The things that we implement are the gated linear unit.
Red line better than green line throughout the scaling trends.
Switch transformer.
I don't know what happened with their biggest run,
but generally speaking, it's got good scaling trends.
And I forgot, oh, mixture of softmaxes.
Actually, we don't do this anymore,
but this is probably an effective intervention
given the scaling trends.
So you see that through these scaling trends,
even though a lot of these papers
were operating on much, much smaller compute scales
than what we operate today, they're
able to see the kinds of architecture trends
that are driving frontier model development back then.
And I think this is why a lot of people use scaling laws
as a really, almost paradigmatic way, saying, "Oh,
if it doesn't show up in the scaling law,
it's not a good intervention."
Because in some ways, a lot of the past work
has captured what we see today.
Good.
OK, going beyond architectures, we
can extend this kind of analysis to all sorts of other things
that we might want to understand.
We might ask, OK, is SGD better or worse than ADAM?
If you do the scaling law analysis, this one's
by Hestness, you'll see very clear trends.
This is once again, the really mysterious thing
of the intercepts are different, but the slopes are very similar.
If you fix the data and you fix the models,
slopes are often very, very similar.
I am very surprised by this every time I see it.
And yet, it's very true.
It's rare to get different slopes,
even with an intervention as big as SGD to ADAM.
If you were the one training with SGD or ADAM,
you would think that's a huge change.
Scaling trends remain roughly the same.
In this case, this is a language modeling
with a recurrent highway net.
Similarly, in lecture 2, I told you about aspect ratios.
How do you pick your depth-to-width trade-off?
And I told you, well, you can just
pick some random number that's somewhat roughly reasonable.
It's like four times the reasonable multiplier.
But if you're doing this kind of scaling analysis,
you could much more precisely what is happening.
So the first thing you could do is
you could look at scaling trends as a function of layers,
and you would immediately see that having extremely few layers
is very, very bad for your model.
If you have one layer, you're not going anywhere.
That's a terrible, terrible scaling trend.
Greater than 1 layer, actually, it's
surprisingly more competitive, although you
do see that at every compute level, more layers, at least
in this case is better.
And if you can do a much more fine-grained study, which
they do in Kaplan, where you try to identify what
you might call scale-invariant quantities,
like the aspect ratio.
The number of layers is not a scale-invariant quantity.
As you make your model bigger, you do want more layers.
But as you make your model bigger,
maybe the aspect ratio, the optimal one should stay the same.
This one is scale invariant.
And so if we look at the aspect ratio,
we see that at different model sizes,
we get basically the same minima around 100d model for every
layer, or maybe a little bit less.
And it does shift a little bit right.
There is a shift towards aspect ratio
that is smaller for deeper models, but for the most part,
the minima stays roughly similar.
You can do similar kinds of analysis
for things like attention head dimension and others.
And if you look at the Kaplan paper,
they do quite a good job at doing all of this.
And this is one way that you can be confident about your scaling
strategy.
So if your scaling strategy is "I'm going to fix my aspect
ratio, and I'm going to scale up,"
you can make plots like this and convince yourself we're probably
good because our optimization shifting too much as I go
to larger and larger and larger models.
One thing that's important, and this is a huge can of worms,
and a sufficiently big can of worms
that I will talk about it on more than one slide,
I will come back, not all parameters are created equal.
And because not all parameters are created equal,
your scaling laws may look good or bad
depending on how you define what a parameter is.
So in the Kaplan paper, they made this observation that
if they drew their scaling laws for depth with the embedding
parameters, they got these very funky-looking scaling laws,
and they said, "Oh, this is no good at all, no good at all."
Because it's no good at all, they
decided that they were going to exclude
all the embedding parameters, and they were only
going to count the non-embedding parameters because you could
justify it to yourself, saying these
are the parameters that are doing computation or whatever.
We're going to see later that this going to have non-trivial implications on the validity
of some of the results.
But the point here is scaling laws aren't magic.
I think Percy likes to make this point,
that scaling laws and all these kinds of predictability
across scales is engineered.
They don't happen automatically.
We need to pick the right kinds of x-axes to look at.
We need to make sure that the hyperparameters for these things
are set right, and only under those conditions
does it become possible to get predictable scaling
across many orders of magnitude compute.
So this is what a lot of scaling law researchers do.
They think about what the right way
is to get very predictable scaling.
Now, related to this, I think are
very interesting recent papers on things like scaling
for mixture of experts.
Now, that mixture of experts is, you would say,
the dominant way of training large models,
it is quite important to think about what is the value
or what is a parameter in this new world
where the number of parameters and the number of parameters
are kind of decoupled.
And there's a nice, clean analysis
by some folks at Apple and MIT that
show the scaling trends as a function of both parameters
and active parameters.
And the cool thing that you see is,
as you start to train bigger and bigger models,
if you increase the amount of total parameters
on the x-axis over here, and you want to minimize your loss,
you're going to end up with more sparse and sparse models.
See how the color becomes darker and darker and darker.
Similarly, here, if you like the number of active parameters
decreases as a function of MoE sparsity.
And you get the result that I think
is somewhat intuitive here, which
is you can draw these surfaces.
For every compute amount, you can ask, OK,
would I rather spend that compute on active parameters
and how much sparsity do I want?
I can vary my sparsity without really changing the amount
of compute that I'm spending.
Now, given that you can ask, OK, what
happens if I add more of empty parameters,
same active parameters, but more total parameters?
As you move from back on the plot
to in the front of the plot, you see the losses are improving.
So in other words, this is saying
that the parameters in an MoE that are not active
are still helping you reduce your loss, which
is kind of cool.
And you can write down what the functional forms of this are.
I won't go into that part in more detail,
but the point here is to say all of these kinds of quantities
that we care about in optimizing MoE
are things that have predictable scaling and regularities.
And the two things I want to now talk about are actually really--
yeah, two things that I now want to talk about.
When you're going to train a new big model,
actually, most of the things that I talk about are fixed.
You're probably all not radical enough
that you're going to switch to an LSTM.
You're probably going to pick like, I don't know,
a DeepSeek-V4-inspired MoE or something.
And you're probably going to pick architecture choices that
are tried and tested.
You're not going to really throw everything out.
But two things that you really do
have to maybe reinvent in some sense
is the batch size and the learning rate.
If you train your deep learning models,
you know that you have to be very careful
about the combination of your batch size and learning rate.
You change one, you have to change the other.
Now, batch size, from the previous lecture,
is very tricky for another reason.
We want the batch size to be as big as possible
because a big batch size gives us opportunity
for parallelization.
Remember, data parallel requires large batch size.
So now, having said all that, what we really want to
is how large can we make our batch size
before we start to suffer?
That's the relevant systems question.
And you also want to know how does that change
as a function of model size.
So given that preface, there is this very important idea
that is used in a variety of papers
and talked about very frequently,
called the critical batch size.
The critical batch size is roughly this idea that
up until a certain point, when you
start to get diminishing returns,
there are returns, perfect returns, to increased batch size.
So I might call this the noise-limited regime.
So in the noise-limited regime, every additional element
that you throw in your batch reduces the gradient noise
in your SGD step.
And since you're variance-limited,
that reduction in variance is very, very helpful.
That gives you big returns.
So this is the regime in which you have perfect scaling.
You're doing about as well as you can,
given the amount of extra examples that you're processing.
As you get to a certain point where
you've reached the noise scale of your gradients,
you get to a point where you are no longer variance-limited.
You're now bias-limited.
What does that mean?
Well, remember, in gradient descent,
you're looking at the local structure of your objective.
You don't have a global view of where the minimum is.
So no matter how low noise I am, I'm
only going to point in this light blue direction over here.
And there's always a disagreement
between my local descent direction
and where the global optimum is.
Because of that, at a certain point,
I'm going to get diminishing returns
because now my limiting factor is no longer variance.
It is this bias term.
So now I'm bias-limited past this point over here.
And so critical batch is kind of a rule of thumb,
you might call it, or a convenient trade-off point where
you say this is the point at which we're starting
to cross over from our perfect scaling
regime to our ineffective scaling regime.
And so it gives you a good rule of thumb
of where to be setting your batch size if you want
your batch size to be as big as possible without suffering
these huge efficiency losses.
Hopefully, that idea is very clear.
Now, critical batch size is kind of a strange object.
It is derived from a variety of complicated calculations
about the local quadratic approximations to the objective.
But I will maybe give you the mechanical steps
of what is actually used to estimate this quantity.
So what you do is first, you pick a target loss.
Target loss might be some numbers that you want to hit.
So your goal is to hit this target loss
as quickly as possible.
That's my goal right now.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to sweep
over all the different batch sizes or number
of different batch sizes, and I'm
going to write down the number of steps that I needed
to reach my target loss, and the number of examples
that were needed to get to that target loss.
Of course, number one and two are related by a batch size factor.
The number of steps times my batch size
is equal to the number of examples.
Now, through some calculations, OpenAI folks, McCandless
and others, argue that this is the rough functional form
that we should follow, that the number of steps that you need
and the number of examples that you need
are inversely related, with this estimate, which
is the minimum number of possible steps
and the minimum number of examples,
normalizing these two quantities.
And so there's a trade-off between these two.
If you want to minimize the number of examples,
you're going to have a lot of steps.
And if you want to minimize the number of steps,
you're going to need a lot of examples.
That's a very natural trade-off.
And if you increase or decrease your batch size,
you're going to have trade-offs that go one side or the other.
Now, they argue the goal now should
be to balance these two sides.
I want to make sure that my number of steps term
and the number of examples terms are roughly
balanced with each other.
And if you solve for that, you're
going to get this particular solution, which
is that the critical batch size is
the minimum number of examples that I
need divided by the minimum number of steps that I need.
And these two are estimated by fitting this to the observed
data that I have.
This is going to balance both sides of the equation.
It's going to give me a little bit more number of steps
than optimal.
It's going to require a little bit more examples than optimal,
but it balances the two sides.
And you can think of this as optimizing the convergence rate
without blowing up the number of steps that you need.
There's another added point that I won't really
belabor because this gets even more into the weeds.
You should really read the critical batch size paper
if you're interested into this, where one of their arguments
is estimating this is quite complicated.
You can do this by just looking at the ratio
of the gradient covariance in the squared norm
of your gradient.
So why is that even in the scaling lecture?
This is a thing that is not really related to scaling so far.
The reason why this is in the scaling lecture
is because, first of all, the critical batch size
is a reasonable batch size to pick.
That's a batch size that balances convergence rate
and the size of the batch.
So if I want to pick my batch size equal to my critical batch
size, you might ask, how does this thing
scale as a function of my target loss?
Target loss can be thought of as compute.
If I want to have a model that is better and better and better,
what is the batch size that I should use?
And the reason why this isn't the scaling law lecture
is as you go down in scale in the loss, so your loss is
improving, the amount of critical batch size increases.
And it increases in this very predictable way, which
is once again, a power law.
So this is the relationship that they argue,
which is roughly inverse polynomial in batch size.
So given this, this is actually quite nice
because what this is saying is if you have
a really large-scale training run where you go all
the way to the right of this plot,
your batch sizes can be quite large.
And that makes sense.
As you get closer and closer and closer to the minimum,
the value of variance reduction increases.
Because you're trying to optimize finer and finer grained objects, the noise
matters a lot more once you're minimizing really, really
tiny differences.
So that's the batch size story.
The other side-- so the two quantities,
remember, that you're going to always have to tune
is batch size and learning rate.
The learning rate side of the story
is also a little bit complicated.
I'll go into this much more detail in the advanced scaling
lecture.
But learning rates generally shift.
I think this is a good mental picture for how
to think about learning rates in the standard world
that you start with, which is, let's say,
that you have just like a MLP.
Just a standard neural network of some kind.
I'm not going to do depth scaling.
I'm only going to do width scaling.
Now, if I'm doing width scaling, the bigger
my model, the bigger my model, the smaller
my learning rate should be.
And the reason why my learning rate should be smaller
is because I have bigger, more parameters,
I'm changing more things at once.
Maybe I should move less.
It kind of makes sense.
And in fact, there's a rule of thumb
that maybe you want to scale by 1 over the width.
That's a very commonly known rule of thumb
that you want to just decrease the learning rate regularly
as a function of your width, and that
will give you a rule of thumb to scale your learning rate.
There is another school of thought,
or another set of tricks that people do,
which is that people also rescale
the network in various ways.
They will change the initialization sizes,
and they will change the step sizes
of the optimizer for various parts of the network
in order to force the model to have the same learning rate
minimum across scales.
And this is an idea that is called muP and others like it.
Some people have reported great success
with these kinds of approaches, others
have reported less success.
The two ways, basically, of setting a learning rate
for large-scale runs really is captured in this plot.
In one way, you can try to estimate
what these minima are and try to predict
what your minimum will be.
And the way in which the minimum changes is pretty predictable,
so this is not a crazy idea.
Or you can reparameterize your model
to try to keep the learning rate minimum the same,
and then just pick your best learning rate and go.
Those are the two philosophies to picking your learning rate.
Both of them have been applied successfully at scale.
There are large-scale training runs
that have used both approaches.
I think anecdotally it does seem more people are maybe favoring
the scaling law approach, but both are certainly
viable approaches.
I'll talk in detail about both of these next lecture.
So before I get into the last part of this lecture,
where I want to talk about not quite
pitfalls but various details of scaling law things,
one thing I want to end this section with
is the idea that upstream and downstream performance
can be quite different.
So if you look at something like log likelihood,
this is from the Yi Tay architectures paper,
you find that perplexity and negative perplexity in this case
parameters are very correlated.
The more parameters you have, the better your model,
very predictably.
This is a very beautiful linear trend.
Now you're like, OK, this is great.
Now we're going to ship our best model.
NL12.
Turns out NL12 is not your best model.
It was actually NL32XL, which was a much worse model
in perplexity.
This is a very common thing that does happen.
Upstream and downstream are often correlated.
This is probably one of the worst correlations
that I've seen from upstream to downstream.
But I think it's very, very important
to remember that scaling laws, generally speaking, are objects
that you want to apply on the perplexity side.
They're very clean, they're very regular,
they're very predictable.
But transfer from perplexity to downstream
is a lot less certain than it might initially seem.
This is a place where you want to be very cautious.
And as an anecdote, I have former students
that have gone and done post-training of various places,
and they always complain.
They're like, "Oh, those pre-training people,
they hand you this model.
They are like, the perplexity is good.
It's all your problem now."
But it's often the problems have started
at the pre-training side.
So you don't want to be one of those people.
You want to really think about transfer as well,
not just focus on perplexities.
OK, so maybe this is surprising, maybe this is not.
But the point that I want to drill in here
is that before you do your big training run,
you should have a rough idea of what you're going to see.
Not just is it going to train at all.
In fact, if you do scaling laws, you
should be able to actually predict fairly precisely
the numerical values, almost, of how good
your run is going to be.
If I choose one optimizer versus the other,
what will the gain be?
You should be able to predict that.
So the scaling law-based procedure
is to say I'm going to train a bunch of smaller models,
I'm going to establish some of a scaling law
by fitting these lines onto log-log plots.
And then if the fit is good enough,
I'm going to have some confidence that the gap will
persist, and then I'm just going to deploy that
onto my large-scale training run.
This is the naive version of a scaling law procedure,
but I think one that is reasonably
accurate for how you might think about these things in practice.
What else are you going to do?
Just deploy a run out of nowhere?
Probably not.
OK, I can pause here and take some questions
before I get into the last part of this lecture.
Yes.
For each of the data points on the scaling law,
how do you think about variance?
How many runs do you do?
And is aggregation usually like the average,
or do you take min or max depending on [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, I think in most cases, if not all cases that I've seen,
those are singletons.
And the reason why it's a singleton
is because when you're looking at perplexities,
perplexities are very, very clean.
These objects, if you rerun them,
they're probably like the variances
in the second decimal place or something
because the training data is very
homogeneous, you've got a lot of it, your eval sets are very big.
You've really pushed the variance very, very low
on these things.
But if you're doing something like learning rate or critical batch
size scaling laws, you will see some truly horrendous stuff.
I do think people do some variance reduction,
but it's actually not that common as common
as it should be, maybe.
Yes.
Do people use just downstream metrics directly
instead of using perplexity?
Yeah, people do scaling laws directly on downstream metrics,
but that has the same problem as this.
So I think the way to think about scaling laws
is to really reliably establish at least one thing.
So the way to think about it is, let's say
I see something like this, I have
a strong belief that this transformer
line is going to continue.
This is a very regular trend.
And it might curve a little bit, but we
do think there's probably some regularity here.
But instead, imagine this was a very noisy jaggedy line
of this form.
You would not really know what is going on.
You would say, I maybe believe that it will go on,
but maybe it's a line, maybe it's a curve.
So I think the general--
if I'm trying to explain the philosophy of this stuff,
is to say, OK, let's start with the low variance measurement
and then establish scaling regularity there and then rely
on some belief about transfer or establish transfer
or elsewhere to try to show that would transfer over
to downstream.
Yeah.
So some of these are [INAUDIBLE],
and some are just [INAUDIBLE] loss.
When do you do either?
I see, yes.
You fit to test loss when you're doing good scientific practice,
like Kaplan 2021.
But realistically, all the models, except for a very few,
like the infinite compute one and the repetition stuff,
unless you're doing some of that, you're doing one-pass SGD.
So the generalization gap for all of these models
is very, very small.
So train and val are very similar.
I've seen some pre-training code bases that don't even
have validation loss.
Because if you're doing one pass, most likely
your train and val are very, very close.
That's why a lot of these plots exchange those two,
because they're all in the one-pass regime.
Good question, though.
OK, all right, we will continue to move on to--
sorry, I moved on too far backwards here.
OK, so now I'm going to talk about one
of the most well-known uses of a scaling law.
Even though you might not personally be using this,
you've certainly used the rule of thumb at some point.
And also, I think because this set of things
will tell us something really interesting about the actual
execution of a scaling law.
OK, the motivating question is, do I
want more data or bigger models?
So the resource that you have, the resource
that you have to spend, is compute.
Someone's going to hand you metaphorically a certain amount
of FLOPs.
And you're going to take those FLOPs,
and you're going to spend them somehow
on—if you remember Percy's very first lecture, it's
going to be data times the parameters is roughly
your FLOPs, linear in that.
So do I want more data or more models?
Well, we know that if we take a teeny tiny model
and we dump tons of data into it, that will just be wasted.
That's the dark purple line at the very top here.
I've taken a teeny tiny language model,
and I've passed a huge amount of data into it,
and this thing has been flat for a very long time.
This is a complete waste of compute.
You would have much rather trained this big yellow model
to the same amount of tokens or even earlier
on, if you're having the same amount of compute.
Now, if you could understand the interaction of how
data amount and model size come together to give you
performance, if you understood that relationship,
you could optimize this very precisely.
And so there are scaling laws that are more advanced
and relate kind of joint behaviors of objects.
So almost simultaneously, Kaplan and Rosenfeld
both proposed these functional forms,
which are roughly equivalent, describing
how the size of the model and the amount of data
relate to the error.
Rosenfeld is very simple.
It's really just the sum of two inverse terms.
These are two scaling laws that are added together.
And Kaplan is a little bit more complicated,
but it's roughly the same idea.
And if you look at, think about the limits,
this is very intuitive.
If I have an infinite amount of data, then what happens?
Then this goes to 0.
You're basically model-size limited.
You become a pure model size scaling law.
If I send my model size to infinity,
then I'm going to be bounded by data.
I'm going to have a pure data scaling law.
So it makes sense if you take the limits of both of these.
It's often a good idea if someone tells you a scaling law
to take the limits of all the variables
to understand the behavior of the system.
Now, the thing that's kind of cool
is Rosenfeld and many others that
have proposed these kinds of joint scaling laws
show that these things fit quite well, even if you extrapolate.
So what you're going to do is you're
going to fit on these green points, which is a low compute
regime and low data regime.
You never see things that have either high data or high model
sizes.
And then you can extrapolate on the basis
of these tiny runs in this corner over here
to essentially this high compute or high data, high model size
regime.
And you can very accurately predict the error
based on your predictions.
Great predictions.
And so once you have that, now what you can do is to say,
well, I have a fixed amount of FLOPs subject to my FLOPs
constraints, minimize this.
That's a simple nonlinear optimization problem.
You can do that to solve for this.
Now, both Kaplan and Rosenfeld provide equations of this form.
What do they say?
Well, if you look at Kaplan, and they solve for this equation,
they say something like this.
Well, the amount of--they always flip this.
It confuses me.
The amount of data it should be C to the 0.73,
and the amount of model size should be C to the 0.27.
Is that reversed?
I think it's reversed, sorry.
N should be the amount of parameters
and D should be the amount of data.
And so tokens per parameters decreases with C.
So as you increase the compute amounts,
this prescription by Kaplan tells
you to train bigger and bigger and bigger models.
And so if you were around in the days of GPT-3,
it kind of shocks me to think that there
are people who were not, you would
know that there was a period where everyone was
training these gigantic models.
Like hundreds of billions of parameters
of models, trillion-parameter dense models, what have you.
And part of that was driven by this.
They saw GPT-3, they saw these Kaplan predictions,
and they said, "Wow, I'm going to do my big training runs
on these gigantic model size models."
But a few years later, in 2022, some folks at DeepMind, Hoffman
et al., came in and they said, well, actually,
these predictions are all terribly off.
You've been training these giant models, these three
stars over here, but actually, those are way too big.
What we should be training instead
is a very different trend, this line on the blue over here,
and we should be training this teal star, which
is a much better model.
So they argued that we should be training much smaller models
relative to this.
And I think, of course, many of you
or all of you probably the Chinchilla paper,
you know what the token multipliers are.
It's 20 tokens to every parameter.
But I think this is useful to go in detail
because the Chinchilla-Kaplan disagreement and all of this
tells us something important about how we should
be thinking about scaling laws.
It's not just something where you turn the crank,
and you get the answer.
It's something that's actually careful and sensitive,
and we have to respect the process.
So I'm going to walk through the Chinchilla paper.
And after I walk through the Chinchilla paper,
I'm going to talk about why the Kaplan and Chinchilla
papers disagree and what that means for you.
So the Chinchilla author suggests three different ways
of fitting scaling laws.
I really like this because it's a way of robustifying yourself
to modeling assumptions you may have made.
And each of these actually is quite a different approach
to estimating the trade-off between model size and data.
And minus method 3, which does differ a little bit,
they mostly agree.
All 1 and 2 both agree that the coefficients
for data and for model size are roughly the same.
0.5, 0.5, 0.49, 0.51.
Method 3 does differ, 0.46 and 0.54, but we'll talk about why
later.
Kaplan et al., of course, have a very big difference
between the two, which is why they were training big models
at big, big compute sizes.
Method number 1 from Chinchilla is
what I might call the lower envelope method.
And this is the method that was also being used partially
by Kaplan to try to figure out what the right scaling was.
And so what you do is you take all of your training runs.
So each one of these colored lines is a training curve.
And what you want to do is you want
to actually take the lower envelope of these training curves.
Because a lower envelope point on this training curve,
that means that for a particular FLOP,
this is the best loss that I ever achieved for that FLOP
on any training run.
So I can take all of the lower envelope
points at the very bottom here at the high compute regime,
and then I can plot all those points
to see how big were the models that each of these FLOP points
intersected.
Because each of these points is a training
run with a model size.
And if I scatter plot that, I will get a nice linear trend.
And that will give me one way of estimating the optimal trade-off
between FLOP to parameters.
And that gives one answer, which is for their compute budget,
they should train a 67 billion parameter model.
This is a nice and simple way, but very tricky defining things
like what is the lower envelope, and so on and so forth.
There's definitely some tricky parts.
Method 2 is IsoFLOP.
This is now very popular.
It's also very easy and very robust.
This is probably my personal favorite method.
And what you do is, for this, you
pick a bunch of different FLOPS budgets.
So I have a different range of FLOPS budgets going in factors
of 3 in this case or 1, 3, 6.
And what you do is for each FLOP budget,
you're going to essentially sweep the space.
So here I have one variable, which
is the parameter-to-data trade-off.
So for each FLOP budget, I'm going
to sweep over the parameter to data trade-off, fixing my FLOPS.
So I double my data size, I half my model size,
so on and so forth.
And that will generate a sequence of training runs
whose terminal loss is going to sweep out some of curve.
So each one of these colored sets of points
is a fixed FLOP run.
Each point is sweeping across different parameters,
and of course, it's implicitly sweeping over data as well.
Now, the nice thing now is I can take the minimum over each
of these runs, or even fit a quadratic
and take the minimum over the quadratics,
and then I can draw a line through all
of the bottoms of the quadratics,
or take the bottom of the quadratics
and plot them as a function of FLOPS to parameters.
And that will give me another prediction,
which agrees very closely.
These is $63 billion parameters for my compute budget.
Now, the final approach that we can do
is actually the maybe most natural one,
as suggested by the Rosenfeld paper as well as the Kaplan
paper, because both of them are propose
a hypothesized functional form for how model
size 和数据与 loss 相关。
所以如果你有这样的联合函数形式，你可以做的是
你可以取一大堆你已经做过的训练运行，
然后你可以拟合你的 loss landscape，也就是
你假设的函数形式，
然后你可以直接做曲线拟合
来估计你的缩放定律中的系数。
这是最暴力的方式。
你有一个假设的关系
在 loss、数据量和模型大小之间，
训练一堆模型，做曲线拟合。
希望这相当直接——你如何做到这一点。
当然，如果你在用这种方法，你如何进行
曲线拟合非常重要。
现在，你在拟合这些曲面，
有很多变量，这有点棘手。
这个东西也有一些棘手之处，就像方法 1 一样。
所以这不像
也许 FLOPS 那样直接。
所以现在我们已经讨论了 Chinchilla 做了什么，
它看起来与
Kaplan 所做的没有本质区别。
并不是 Kaplan 做了什么疯狂的事，然后
Chinchilla 的作者做了更聪明的事，而你
说：“哇，为什么我们不从一开始就这么做？”
他们都做了相当合理的事情。
但如果我们看他们的缩放预测，
它们非常不同。
事后看来，我们通常倾向于同意
Chinchilla 的作者有更多正确的缩放。
如果你做你自己的 Chinchilla 风格分析，
你会发现缩放可能更接近 Chinchilla。
那么，为什么会有这么大的差异，当
他们都在拟合这些联合缩放定律时？
好的，所以这是我认为我们
进入缩放定律是如何制定的这些混乱现实的地方。
缩放定律真的会变化，取决于
你实现缩放定律的精确方式，
你使用的超参数设置，
甚至 x 轴是什么。
有一篇非常好的论文。
哦，不，我把作者遮住了。
我之后可以把它粘贴到课程的 Slack 里。
——叫《Resolving Discrepancy to Compute-Optimal Scaling
of Language Models》。
Yair 是最后一位作者。
他曾是这里的学生。
他们展示——基本上，首先他们
用大致 Kaplan 的设置
复现了 Kaplan 的结果。
然后他们说，好吧，让我们
改变参数的计数方式。
这会让曲线稍微移动一点。
然后他们说，好吧，让我们
改变学习率预热的方式。
这会让曲线稍微移动一点。
然后让我们再稍微调一调优化器。
然后他们就得到了和 Chinchilla 完全一致的结果。
所以他们的论点是，这里存在
一系列看起来非常微小的决定，最终
在 Kaplan 缩放定律
和 Chinchilla 缩放定律之间造成了这么大的差距。
我会解释这些步骤各自
是什么，并不是说这是最重要的单一因素，
而是也想向你强调，这里的细节有多么重要。
所以第一个箭头，我们从 Kaplan
到蓝线的这一步，就是参数的计数方式。
所以记住，在 Kaplan 中，我说过，好吧，
如果他们把嵌入参数
也算进去，就会看到这些奇怪的现象。
所以他们排除了嵌入参数。
这通常是可以接受的做法。
但他们还做了一件真正把他们搞砸的事，
就是他们也排除了最后一层的参数
计数，也就是 softmax 那些。
因为在许多模型中，嵌入层和最后一层
线性层是互为对偶的。
它们有相同的形状。
嵌入矩阵是词表大小乘以隐藏维度。
输出矩阵是隐藏维度乘以词表大小。
And because they're the same shape,
they said, well, let's just exclude both of those.
It turns out whether you include or exclude
those has a big material impact on the shape of the scaling law.
They also found-- this is much more of an oversight,
more than a genuine difference in opinion,
that a lot of the models that were being trained in Kaplan
were very small.
And in fact, they were so small that they were not actually
converging by the time that the learning rate warm up was done.
So their learning rates were set very suboptimally.
And because of that, their models weren't fully converged.
And then finally, they found that Kaplan et al. was fixing
one big batch size, and those big batch sizes
were suboptimal for the smaller models.
And therefore, if you tune that correctly
and you use varying batch sizes, you
end up getting this thing that agrees exactly with Chinchilla.
So I think each of these might seem
like a very minor difference, but if you change up
these really minor differences, you
can get big shifts in the scaling law.
And one thing I like to emphasize
is that scaling laws are lower bounds in some sense.
They're kind of saying, if I continue this recipe
and I scale it up, then this is what I will get.
But if you're scaling up a recipe that you don't want
to scale up, your warmup is kind of crazy,
or your batch sizes are crazy, you're
going to get bad scaling laws.
So you want to be as close to the proper full run as possible.
There's another paper that does another very interesting thing
to try to study the difference between Kaplan and Chinchilla
scaling laws.
It's by Pearce and Song.
And what they do, and I think this is very clever,
is they don't train any models.
They just take the Chinchilla training
curves or the implied functional form of the Chinchilla training
curves.
They just plot them out and they say, well,
based on these implied training curves, which
are simulated purely from Chinchilla,
they generate what the implied training curves will
be for Kaplan if you ignore the embedding parameters
and you scale way down, and what happens
if you use the total parameter count instead.
And what they find is really two effects.
One is that Kaplan is operating at a much lower compute scale,
so they're very sensitive to small changes,
and actually ignoring the non-embedding parameter
is a sufficiently big change to mess up the result relative
to Chinchilla.
So their argument is slightly different from Yair and others,
which is that here, actually, it's
the size of the compute scale plus the slight non-linearity
induced by non-embedding parameters that's
causing this disagreement.
So this is really starting to get into the weeds.
But I hope you appreciate the importance
of paying attention to detail.
And I think a lot of the work that goes on
in establishing reliable scaling laws
is about figuring out what the right regime is
so that you can get reliable scaling across compute scales.
The final thing, and this is really just more of something
that I just find amusing more than anything else, which
is that Chinchilla is this paper that takes down
the Kaplan paper in a way.
It's like, oh, you guys were very wrong.
But there was this one remaining mystery,
which is that Chinchilla method three never agreed
with Chinchilla method 1 and 2.
And the numbers look small.
And the authors are very unperturbed about this,
but I think the implications are quite non-trivial.
If you look at this, methods 1 and 2 basically
say the amount of parameters and tokens should scale together.
So there should be a fixed ratio between the two.
This is where the Chinchilla factor of 20 comes from.
If you look at number 3, the exponents are different.
This means if you scale up your compute,
eventually, actually, in this case,
you're going to have way more tokens than you
are going to have parameters.
So it's going to be actually a very different scaling
conclusion asymptotically than the other ones.
And so it turns out that I was certainly not the only one who
was perturbed about this, except some folks at Epoch AI
did something about being perturbed.
They couldn't get either the raw data or the code.
So what they did was they extracted the data from plots
in the paper, and they refitted the method 3 regressions.
They extracted the data from the paper.
And given that data, they fitted that 2D surface or 3D surface
that was proposed.
And then, what they showed is actually
the original paper must have underfitted the original data.
And if they redid the curve fitting,
they could get much lower losses relative to what
the proposed scaling law in the Chinchilla paper.
And in fact, if you follow the refitted model,
you got almost exactly D over 20 is
20 rule of thumb from the Chinchilla paper,
which is really a funny conclusion,
I think, to the Chinchilla paper, where in the end
it turns out that the authors were more right than they knew.
Actually, they had made a mistake,
and that was the only reason why method 3 disagreed
from methods 1 and 2.
So it's a nice conclusion to know that the method was
robust after all.
OK, so that's the end of the Chinchilla saga in some ways.
But I will end this section by saying you probably don't
want the Chinchilla factor.
At this point, I think this is a pretty common knowledge thing.
But if you're training a production model,
you don't really care about saving training compute
for the most part.
You can look at all sorts of external surveys
that people have done of how frontier labs are
spending their compute.
Most of the compute is not going into training runs.
Most of the compute is actually going into R&D and serving.
And given that, especially for serving, what you want to do
is you want small models that are capable.
You do not want big, bloated models that cost a lot to serve,
even if that minimizes training cost.
And so what you really want is something that you would call
"overtrained."
I put that in quotes because, really, overtraining
is what we want.
That's the right amount of training.
And if you look at all the models that were released
in the early days, like GPT-3--
this was under-trained for sure, three tokens per parameter.
Chinchilla gets to the modern ratio of 20 per parameter.
And then for a while, people were at 20 per parameter.
And this is the era, I think, where
there wasn't that much serving of these models.
The models were cool, but it wasn't being served at scale.
And then as you start to move to eras where serving becomes very
real, now you're overtraining these models,
and now you've moved into MoEs, and you're
making all these trade-offs to optimize inference serving.
So I think Chinchilla is important,
not because I think the 20-to-1 ratio is the one golden ratio.
If you're doing stuff for research, it might be.
But I think the reason why it's important
is because it tells us quite a bit about how
we should be fitting scaling laws
and how to think about scaling laws.
OK, one final thing I'll end with Chinchilla-wise
and otherwise for scaling is IsoFLOP
have been one of the things that, I think,
has a research tool have endured.
IsoFLOP are very easy to execute.
You fix a FLOPS budget, and then you
sweep over all of the other degrees of freedom
to see what the surface looks like.
And this gives you, in general, fairly reliable readings
of how different parameters vary as a function
of your free parameters.
People have done this for-- or actually, one of my students
did this for diffusion models.
The MoE study I talked about was an IsoFLOP-style design.
If you're ever in a situation where you're thinking,
how am I going to decide all these trade-offs,
IsoFLOP is always a good default.
OK, so to wrap up everything for today,
there's this idea that we have this log-linear regularity
between the amount of resources we put in
and the performance we get out.
And it extends to a wide variety of things, model parameters,
compute, sparsity level of your MoE.
And that lets you do a lot of the things
that I was talking about earlier, as arbitrary choices,
but do it in a much more evidence-driven way, hopefully.
And so this allows us to have engineering at scale
without explicitly relying on doing big model training runs.
And hopefully, you remember, I think all
the different components here.
Data scaling is this very natural object,
just the exponent is a little bit strange.
Model scaling allows you to do all these cool engineering
things.
And then finally, scaling is this very cool,
robust predictor, let's call it, for how
to try to do engineering at a large scale.
And thanks.
The next lecture, I think, will be Percy on inference.
But after that, we will return to more advanced niche scaling
topics.
[APPLAUSE]